"Why People Gain Weight in the Fall"
SAD doesn’t just stand for
standard American diet.
There’s a condition known as
seasonal affective disorder
that’s characterized by increased
appetite and cravings,
along with increased sleepiness and
lethargy that begins in autumn
when light exposure starts to dwindle.
This now appears to just
represent the far end
of a normal spectrum
of a human behavior.
We all appear to eat more
as the days get shorter.
There"s a “marked seasonal rhythm” to
calorie intake with greater meal size,
eating rate, hunger, and overall
calorie intake in the fall.
In preparation for winter, some animals
hibernate, doubling their fat stores
with autumn abundance to deal with
the subsequent scarcity of winter.
Genes have been identified in humans
that are similar to hibernation genes,
which may help explain why we
exhibit some of the same behaviors.
The autumn affect isn’t subtle.
Researchers calculated a
222-calorie difference
between calorie intake
in the fall versus spring.
And this isn’t just because it’s colder,
since we eat more in the
fall than the winter.
It appears we’re just
genetically programmed
to prep for the deprivation of
winter that no longer comes.
It’s remarkable that in this day and
age of modern lighting and heating
that our bodies would still pick
up on the environmental cues
of the changing seasons enough to affect
such a major influence
on our eating patterns.
Unsurprisingly, bright light
therapy is used to treat
seasonal affective disorder,
nearly tripling the likelihood
of remission compared to placebo.
Though it’s never been directly tested,
it can’t hurt to take the dog out
for some extra autumn morning
walks to maybe help fend off
some of the coming holiday
season weight gain.
It’s funny: people blame the
holidays for overeating,
but maybe instead of the holidays
causing heightened intake,
maybe the heightened intake
that goes with the fall
caused the holidays to be scheduled
then in the first place.
Regardless… other “specific
recommendations
for the prevention of obesity…by
improving the circadian system health,”
based on varying degrees of evidence
include sleeping during the night
and being active during the day.
Sleep enough, at least 7
or 8 hours a night.
Early to bed, early to rise.
Short naps are fine.
Contrary to popular belief,
daytime napping does not appear
to adversely impact sleep at night.
Avoid bright light exposure at night and
sleep in total darkness when possible.
Make breakfast or lunch your
biggest meal of the day,
don’t eat or exercise right before bed,
and avoid eating at night completely.